ajitjaincse@gmail.com https://ajitjain.github.io

Ajit Jain

ABOUT

Computer Science Ph.D. with 15+ years of experience in conceptualizing, developing, and evaluating state-of-the-art solutions, connecting ideas from human-computer interaction, artificial intelligence, information retrieval, information visualization, and software engineering.

7+ years of experience in managing people, helping them grow and realize their potential. Both as an individual contributor and manager, I have helped create a culture of excellence in the teams I have been a part of, taking them to new heights and delivering unprecedented value to stakeholders.

Citations: 170+ (Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=B8H-aLkAAAAJ)

- → Best Paper Honorable Mention Award at ACM Creativity & Cognition
- → Best Paper Nomination, Best Student Paper Nomination at ACM Document Engineering

EDUCATION

Texas A&M University

College Station, USA

2015-2021

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Co-Advisors: Dr. Andruid Kerne and Dr. Ruihong Huang

Thesis: How to Support Situated Design Education through AI-Based Analytics

Texas A&M University

College Station, USA

M.S. in Computer Science

2011 - 2014

Advisor: Dr. Andruid Kerne

Thesis: TweetBubble: A Twitter Extension Stimulates Exploratory Browsing

Delhi Technological University

Delhi, India

B.E. in Information Technology

2003-2007

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Full-Time

Oakton, USA Audigent Mar 2022-Present

Distinguished Engineer / Senior Engineer, Data Architecture & Research

- → Led state-of-the-art technology solutions critical to driving executive strategy, conceptualizing and developing them in collaboration with stakeholders across business units.
- → Researched, developed, and productionized new techniques, including AI/ML approaches, for cookieless audiences, audience search, audience configuration, and yield optimization.
- → Filed a patent titled Systems and Method for Simultaneous Relevance and Variety Control in Audience Targeting, addressing the dual needs of scale and specificity.
- → Led and presented Cognitive Audiences technology, a novel, ID-less, turnkey solution addressing 3P cookie deprecation. Launched in collaboration with Experian, the largest credit bureau in the US.
- → Increased revenue—including creation of new revenue streams—through novel cookieless audience solutions, audience curation platforms, and scale maximization approaches.
- → Awarded with spot bonus for scale maximization work toward addressing the simultaneous needs for scale and specificity in audience targeting.
- → Designed, developed, and optimized large-scale data systems focused on deriving audience analytics and presenting them via dashboards.

→ Mentored junior engineers in designing and implementing automation, optimization, and analysis processes.

Amobee Los Angeles, USA

Software Engineer, Data Systems

Jun 2021–Mar 2022

- → Collaborated with stakeholders across business units to identify and disambiguate requirements, as well as to validate that the developed solutions meet or surpass the requirements.
- → Designed, developed, and optimized data pipelines that operate at petabytes scale and deliver ad insights for a range of platforms, including digital and linear media.
- → Created a 4x faster cross-channel report generation workflow, while also eliminating the need for manual intervention at various steps.
- → Investigated machine learning models to optimize data pipeline performance, following extraction of novel insights through exploratory data analysis.
- → Mentored junior engineers in developing and optimizing data pipelines for delivering diverse analytics.

Samsung Noida, India

Lead Engineer / Senior Engineer / Software Engineer

Jul 2007-Aug 2011

- → Played an instrumental role in the commercialization of Java platform for mobile, set-top, and blu-ray product lines, coordinating development across teams in India and S. Korea. Teams' size: 10 members each.
- → Published a first-author research paper at IEEE U-Media titled Modified Programming Language Framework for IVRS Accessibility of Graphical User Interfaces.
- → Developed, ported, and optimized 2D Graphics module of Java Virtual Machine. Created novel MNG animation support in the graphics layer.
- → Mentored junior engineers in implementing graphics rendering and optimizing multithreaded execution.
- → Developed notebook apps focused on remote access and network management, including a Six Sigma project addressing remote desktop performance.
- → Awarded with 'Best Attitude' and 'Extra Mile' awards for outstanding performance and contribution.
- → Developed a web-based software component quality evaluation system, including metrics such as SLOC, coupling, cohesion, and cyclomatic complexity.

Internship

Research Intern

Centrum Wiskunde & Informatica

Amsterdam, Netherlands

Summer 2018

Mentors: Dr. Pablo Cesar and Dr. Abdallah El Ali

- → Identified a research gap in supporting personal health tracker users in understanding their data.
- → Developed surveys to gather needs and evaluate visualizations for users' sensemaking of their sleep data.
- → Identified effective visualizations for sleep tracking through quantitative and qualitative data analyses.

Adobe Research
Data Scientist Intern
Summer 2017

Mentor: Dr. Eunyee Koh

→ Identified a research problem in audience segmentation, engaging in discussions with marketing experts.

- → Developed interactive visualization of large-scale graph data to present audience overlaps across campaigns.
- → Established the system's efficacy through user studies followed by quantitative and qualitative data analyses.

Google Mountain View, USA

Software Engineering Intern

Summer 2016

Mentor: Amos Yoffe

- → Developed module for presenting message results in Android In Apps search, clustered by topic and time.
- → Validated the new presentation method by creating a test dataset of messages and comparing search results.
- → Launched in September 2016, making the feature available worldwide.

Google Summer of Code Student Developer Intern

College Station, USA

Summer 2012

Host Organization: Interface Ecology Lab, Texas A&M University

→ Developed a RESTful service for meta-metadata structured web semantics represented in XML / JSON format.

- → Developed caching, database integration, logging, testing, and deployment modules.
- → Deployed the service in a production environment following a thorough investigation of available web servers.

ACADEMIC RESEARCH PROJECTS

• Design Analytics [Human-Computer Interaction, Artificial Intelligence]

Spring 2017–Spring 2021

A human-centered AI investigation for assisting instructors in assessing a range of visual and conceptual characteristics present within student design work.

- → Engaged co-design discussions and workshops to understand instructors' situated practices and needs.
- → Developed a first-of-its-kind AI recognizer to measure students' use of space and scale in their free-form design work.
- → Deployed AI-based analytics via dashboards, as a technology probe, in situated course contexts.
- → Established efficacy through quantitative precision-recall measures and qualitative analysis of instructor interviews using a grounded theory approach.
- TweetBubble [Human-Computer Interaction]

Fall 2013-Fall 2016

A Chrome Extension for Twitter users to follow @usernames, #hashtags associations without tabs or windows.

- → Developed and deployed Chrome Extension, making it available worldwide.
- \rightarrow Conducted studies during societal events such as the Academy Awards and Super Bowl.
- → Developed ideation metrics of exploratory browsing, including Fluency, Flexibility, and Novelty.
- → Established efficacy through a mixed methods evaluation, including quantitative ideation metrics and qualitative analysis of user experience data using grounded theory.
- Event Indicators [Natural Language Processing]

Spring 2016–Fall 2016

A weakly supervised approach for extracting and clustering event indicators from Twitter social media.

- → Cleaned up event relevant tweets, filtering duplicates arising from exact matches, substrings, punctuations, etc.
- → Applied bootstrapping to acquire a variety of civil unrest event cues, starting from a single strong indicator.
- **BigSemantics** [Software Engineering]

Fall 2012–Fall 2016

A software architecture for developing meta-metadata semantics powered dynamic exploratory browsing interfaces.

- → Developed new data models, extraction rules, and presentation semantics for social media.
- → Developed a RESTful service to facilitate semantics-driven application development across a range of contexts.
- EvolutionWorks [Human-Computer Interaction, Information Retrieval]

Fall 2011–Spring 2012

A free-form, zoomable space facilitating browsing, collection, and sensemaking of research papers interconnections.

- → Developed interface for presenting papers as cards within the free-form zoomable space.
- → Developed algorithm for determining representative terms present within a cluster when the user zooms out.
- → Established efficacy through user studies, comparing the interface with tabbed browsers.
- PhotoNav [Human-Computer Interaction]

Fall 2011–Spring 2012

A mixed reality investigation for assisting pedestrian navigation through the means of photographs.

- → Developed the NavCurator application for the specification of navigation paths over maps.
- → Evaluated handheld and head-mounted displays—through user studies—for assisting pedestrian navigation.

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

• Senior Membership, IEEE

2024

• Highly Useful Review Recognition for ACM Creativity & Cognition

2024

• Spot Bonus for Scale Maximization work at Audigent

2022

Best Paper Nomination at ACM Document Engineering	2021
• Best Student Paper Nomination at ACM Document Engineering	2021
• Student Travel Grant, College of Engineering, Texas A&M	2021
• Best Teaching Assistant Nomination(s), Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Texas A&M	2018-2021
• Outstanding Reviewer Recognition for ACM CHI PLAY Full Papers	2019
• Academy for Future Faculty Certificate, Center for Teaching Excellence, Texas A&M	2018
• Student Travel Grant, College of Engineering, Texas A&M	2017
• Student Travel Grant, National Science Foundation	2017
• Best Paper Honorable Mention at ACM Creativity & Cognition	2015
• Student Travel Grant, College of Engineering, Texas A&M	2015
• Extra Mile Award at Samsung	2010
• Best Project Award(s) at Samsung	2008, 2010
• Best Attitude Award at Samsung	2008
• Six Sigma Green Belt at Samsung	2008

2021

PATENTS

- Jain, A., Griffiths, M., Spiegelman, M., Peng, K., and Stein, D., Predictive Pop, Inc. d/b/a Audigent. Systems and Method for Simultaneous Relevance and Variety Control in Audience Targeting. U.S. Patent Application 18/406,156, filed Jan 7, 2024.
- Subramanian, M., Bansal, R.K., Jain, A., Khandelwal, D., Agrawal, G., Solanki, N. and Thakur, P., Samsung Electronics Co Ltd, 2013. Display Device and Method for Presenting Information on Entities Displayed on Video Content. U.S. Patent Application 13/888,669, filed May 7, 2013.

Manuscripts

- 1. Jain, A., Kerne, A., Fowler, H., Seo, J., Newman, G., Lupfer, N., and Perrine, A. (2024). How Could AI Support Design Education? A Study Across Fields Fuels Situating Analytics. arXiv preprint arXiv:2404.17390.
- 2. **Jain, A.**, Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Britain, G., Perrine, A., Choe, Y., Keyser, J., Huang, R., Seo, J., Sungkajun, A., Lightfoot, R., and McGuire, T. (2024). Indexing Analytics to Instances: How Integrating a Dashboard can Support Design Education. arXiv preprint arXiv:2404.05417.

Refereed Conference Papers

- 1. Jain, A., Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Britain, G., Perrine, A., Choe, Y., Keyser, J., and Huang, R. Recognizing Creative Visual Design: Multiscale Design Characteristics in Free-Form Web Curation Documents. In *Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on Document Engineering (DocEng) 2021*, 1-10 [33%]. Best Paper Nomination, Best Student Paper Nomination.
- 2. Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Linder, R., Qu, Y., Valdez, A., Jain, A., Keith, K., Carrasco, M., Vanegas, J., Billingsley, A. Free-form Web Curation: Strategies for Creative Engagement with Prior Work. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Creativity & Cognition (C&C) 2017*, 380-392 [29%].

- 3. Sharma, H. N., Toups, Z. O., Dolgov, I., Kerne, A., **Jain, A.** Evaluating Display Modalities using a Mixed Reality Game. In *Proceedings of the ACM Annual Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction in Play (CHI PLAY) 2016*, 65-77 [29%].
- 4. Jain, A., Lupfer, N., Qu, Y., Linder, R., Kerne, A., Smith, S. M. Evaluating TweetBubble with Ideation Metrics of Exploratory Browsing. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Creativity and Cognition (C&C) 2015*, 178-187 [28%]. Best Paper Honorable Mention Top 2%.
- Wilkins, J., Järvi, J., Jain, A., Kerne, A., Kejriwal, G., Gumudavelly, V. EvolutionWorks: Towards Improved Visualization of Citation Networks. In Proceedings of the IFIP Conference on Computer-Human Interaction (INTERACT) 2015, 213-230 [29.9%].
- Qu, Y., Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Linder, R., Jain, A. Metadata Type System: Integrate Presentation, Data Models
 and Extraction to Enable Exploratory Browsing Interfaces. In Proceedings of the ACM Engineering Interactive
 Computing Systems (EICS) 2014, 107-116 [18%].
- Fei, S., Webb, A. M., Kerne, A., Qu, Y., and Jain, A. Peripheral Array of Tangible NFC Tags: Positioning Portals for Embodied Trans-Surface Interaction. In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces (ITS) 2013, 33-36 [29%].
- 8. Jain, A. and Singh, S. Modified Programming Language Framework for IVRS Accessibility of Graphical User Interfaces. U-Media, pp.163-167, In *Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Ubi-Media Computing (U-Media) 2011*, 163-167 [34%].

Refereed Workshops and Extended Abstracts

- 1. Britain, G., Jain, A., Lupfer, N., Kerne, A., Perrine, A., Seo, J., Sungkajun, A. Design is (A)live: An Environment Integrating Ideation and Assessment, In Extended Abstracts of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI Late-Breaking Work) 2020, 1-8 [41.8%].
- 2. Jain, A. Measuring Creativity: Multi-Scale Visual and Conceptual Design Analysis. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Creativity & Cognition (C&C) 2017*, Graduate Student Symposium, 490-495.
- 3. Jain, A., Kasiviswanathan, G., and Huang, R. Towards Accurate Event Detection in Social Media: A Weakly Supervised Approach for Learning Implicit Event Indicators. In *Proceedings of the Computational Linguistics* (COLING) Workshop on Noisy User-Generated Text (WNUT) 2016, 70-77.
- 4. Sharma, H. N., Toups, Z. O., **Jain, A.**, Kerne, A. Designing to Split Attention in a Mixed Reality Game. In *Proceedings of the ACM Annual Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction in Play (CHI PLAY) 2015*, 691-696.
- 5. Fei, S., Kerne, A., **Jain, A.**, Webb, A. M., and Qu, Y. Positioning portals with peripheral NFC tags to embody trans-surface interaction. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces (ITS) 2013*, 317-320.

Presentations

• Cognitive Audiences: Powering the Cookieless Future

Jan 2024

Experian Data Scientists and Business Development Leads

• Recognizing Creative Visual Design: Multiscale Design Characteristics in Free-Form Web Curation Documents

Aug 2021

DocEng'21: Document Engineering

• LiveMâché: Ideation on the Web

Sep 2020

Georgia Tech ME 6102: Designing Open Engineering Systems

• Measuring Creativity: Multi-Scale Visual and Conceptual Design Analysis

Jun 2017

C&C'17: Creativity and Cognition (Graduate Student Symposium)

• Towards Accurate Event Detection in Social Media

 $\mathrm{Dec}\ 2016$

COLING'17: Computational Linguistics

• Evaluating TweetBubble with Ideation Metrics of Exploratory Browsing

Jun 2015

C&C'15: Creativity and Cognition

• Programming Language Framework for IVRS Accessibility of Graphical User Interfaces

Jul 2011

UMEDIA'11: Ubi-Media Computing

SKILLS

- Programming Languages: C, C++, Java, Python, Scala, R
- Web Programming: HTML, JavaScript, React, REST, Django, Node.js
- Big Data Technologies: Spark, Kafka, Druid, Airflow
- Machine Learning Libraries: Scikit-learn, TensorFlow, Keras
- Visualization Libraries: D3.js, Three.js, Gephi
- Research Methods: Interviews, Surveys, Observations, Workshops, Grounded Theory, Hypothesis Testing

TEACHING

- Instructor of Record, Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Texas A&M

Spring 2021

CSCE 121 Introduction to Program Design and Concepts (C++)

• Teaching Assistant, Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Texas A&M

Spring 2015–Fall 2020

CSCE 655 Human-Centered Computing

CSCE 482 Senior Capstone Design

CSCE 444 Structures of Interactive Information

CSCE 420 Artificial Intelligence

CSCE 315 Programming Studio

CSCE 206 Structured Programming (C++)

CSCE 121 Introduction to Program Design and Concepts (C++)

MENTORING

• Industry Mentoring, Audigent, Amobee, and Samsung

2009-2011, 2022-Present

Mentor software, data, and full-stack engineers on various aspects of system development, including ideation, architectural design, coding, debugging, evaluation, documentation, and presentation.

• Gabriel Britain, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M

Fall 2019–Spring 2020

Research: Design analytics dashboards and their integration with a multiscale design environment.

- Hannah Fowler, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M

Spring 2018–Fall 2018

Research: A grounded theory analysis of design instructors' teaching and assessment practices and needs.

- Aaron Perrine, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M $\,$

Spring 2018-Fall 2018

Research: Design analytics dashboards and their integration with a multiscale design environment.

• Alex Stacy, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M

Fall 2016

Research: BigSemantics-based wrappers for extracting and presenting information from social media.

SERVICE

• Reviewer		2015–Present
Recognition for Outstanding	g / Highly Useful Reviews at Multiple Venues	
ACM CHI 2024, 2022, 2021, ACM DIS 2022, 2021, 2020, ACM C&C 2024, 2021, 2019 ACM CHI PLAY 2024, 2019 ACM CSCW 2022, 2020, 2010 ACM ISWC 2023 ACM ISS 2023 ACM ICMI 2021 CogSci 2021, 2019 EAI MobiHealth 2020	2019, 2018, 2016 0, 2015 0, 2018, 2017	
• Associate Chair		2021
ACM Creativity & Cognition	n	
• Judge, Student Research	ı Week	2021
Texas A&M University		
• Registration Chair		2019
ACM Creativity & Cognition	n	
• Student Volunteer		2012
Design Computing and Cogn	nition	
References		

Dr. Andruid Kerne Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering Texas A&M University \boxtimes and ruid@ecologylab.net

Dr. Steven M. Smith

Professor Department of Psychology Texas A&M University ⊠ stevesmith@tamu.edu

Dr. Ruihong Huang

Associate Professor Department of Computer Science and Engineering Texas A&M University \boxtimes huangrh@cse.tamu.edu

Dr. Jinsil Seo

Associate Professor Department of Visualization Texas A&M University ⋈ hwaryoung@tamu.edu